<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Treasons anatomie, or, The duty of a loyall subject in vindicating his gracious soveraigne, against those horrid aspertions, cast upon him, concerning his fathers death, the reliefe of the Rochellers, and the rebellion in Ireland, and in way of answer to A declaration, published by the House of Commons, Feb. 15.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077698</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2277:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Treasons anatomie, or, The duty of a loyall subject in vindicating his gracious soveraigne, against those horrid aspertions, cast upon him, concerning his fathers death, the reliefe of the Rochellers, and the rebellion in Ireland, and in way of answer to A declaration, published by the House of Commons, Feb. 15.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3-15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare. Anno Dom. 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>La Rochelle (France) --  History --  Siege, 1627 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151809:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151809:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TREASONS <hi>ANATOMJE</hi> Or The Duty of a Loyall SUBJECT In Vindicating His gracious <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> againſt thoſe horrid Aſpertions, caſt upon Him, conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning His Fathers Death, The reliefe of the <hi>Rochellers,</hi> and The Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in way of Anſwer to a Declaration, publiſhed by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Feb.</hi> 15.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 89. Ver. 48.</bibl>
               <p>Lord where are Thy old loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: which Thou ſwareſt unto <hi>David</hi> in Thy truth?</p>
               <bibl>Ver. 49.</bibl>
               <p>Remember (O Lord) the rebuke that thy Servants have: and how I doe beare in my boſome the rebuke of many People.</p>
               <bibl>Ver. 50.</bibl>
               <p>Wherewith thine Enemies have blaſphemed Thee, and ſlandered the Foot-ſteps of thine Anoynted: Prayſed be the Lord for evermore.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 7. Ver. 8.</bibl>
               <p>The Lord ſhall Iudge the People, give ſentence with mee O Lord: according to Thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouneſſe, and according to the innocencie that is in mee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pro. 19. ver. 9.</bibl>
               <p>A falſe witneſſe ſhall not be unpuniſhed: but Hee that ſpeaketh lies ſhall periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſ. 125.</bibl>
               <p>This I had: becauſe I kept thy Commandements.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Proverbs 20. ver. 2.</bibl>
               <p>The feare of a King is like the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a <hi>Lyon;</hi> Hee that provoketh Him to anger, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt His owne Soule.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 26. ver. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Bee thou my Iudge O God, for I have walked innocently: My truſt hath beene alſo in the Lord, therefore ſhall I not fall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perſpice finem.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151809:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151809:2"/>
            <head>The Preface To all his Majeſties Subiects.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Deare Countrymen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earing of a Poyſonous and till now) unheard of peece of treaſon lately hatched, wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned by the way of Articles) helliſh and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous imputations of his ſacred Majeſty, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing him to be the Author of his Fathers death, Opugnant to the Reliefe of <hi>Rochell.</hi> And the Cauſer or Abetter of the Rebelion in <hi>Ireland.</hi> &amp;c. I thought it very meet (being both bound in conſcience by my allegeance and alſo for the referrence) every religious Man ought to have the truth violated againſt any perſon, more eſpecially, and in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable meaſure, when he; ſo gracious a Prince, is brought upon the Stage of opprobrious calumnie, falſe-witneſſe, or rather ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers (for witneſſes, Maugre all their perjury they can, produce none) raiſing up and laying to his Charge, things that he knew not. Let any man that hath but common ſence, Judge how their other Arguments do hang together, and thereby he may the eaſier diſcerne of theſe laſt Superlatively, trayterous and moſt inhumane
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151809:3"/>accuſations, being by no other meanes able to diſturbe his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Patience [admired of all the World] think at laſt by theſe Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpude ſuggeſtions to overcome the ſmooth [and as neere as a man could be] immaculate current of his paſſions to ſuch a vehemencie and vigour of Spirit as ſhall ſome way prejudice him in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and ſupporting of ſo righteous a cauſe as he now in his royall and religious perſon ſuffereth for being debarred the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that the very meaneſt of his Subjects enjoy; See their Horrid'ſt plots, pry into the ſinke of their Diverliſh, intentions, and thou ſhalt plainly find that their maine deſigne, is to render our Sacred Soveraignee odious to the Ignorant Communalty, whereby their Arbitrary Government may creep in; and then [how many Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament men, ſo many monſtrous Kings, How many Monſters. ſo many Tyrants] I'le keepe thee no longer at the Gate, Enter, and view their Infernall Stratagem within doores.</p>
            <p>Bluſh oh Heavens at the diveliſh, Impudency of this forlorne wretches O Earth why cannot thy mouth open, ſwallowing their Dathans, and covering the Abiriums of theis catiffe tymes? O Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters how ſtands it, you rageing waters orewhelme not theſe ten thouſand more then Egyptian cruelty? how long will it bee ere theſe Iulianiſts cry <hi>viciſti Nazarene,</hi> or Ieſus thou haſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend? ſhall the Enemy blaſpheme thy glorious name, O God for ever unpuniſhed, or the preſumption of them that hate thee increaſe thus ever more and more? Shall thy deareſt ſervant, and our dread ſoveraigne be thus intollorably ſlandered, and not their names periſh? Shall not all the loyall blood that was ſhed from the blood of Noble <hi>Stratford</hi> to the blood of that worthy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre <hi>Burleigh</hi> be required of this viperous generation of cruel and inhumaine Canniballs? How curriſhly doe theſe cinnicall dogges barke and houle at the ſplendor (though clouded by inhumaine Treaſon) of our Rroyall and unſtained ſtarre, and be right ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of juſtice. The comfort (though now the Corazive) of all that have the leaſt glimpſe of Knowledg, or ſence of the feare of God. But to the intended Subject, and firſt to that Helliſh Weſt. minſterian lye, of his Majeſties having a hand in the death of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Father, who (as it is knowne to all of any capacity, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151809:3"/>of this City) dyed in a good old age, having finiſhed his courſe, and left his royall Houſe in order, his diſeaſe being an Ague and further to convince theſe helliſh vipers, there have been divers Chiurgions and others (by the Houſe examined) who were at the embalming, and encoffening of that generally lamented Prince, who have Iuſtified his corps to be as free from any the leaſt imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or change of colour as could be, 'twould make the ruth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſeſt and moſt Tiger ſpirited man in the world repine, except the drove at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>What Marble heart could but molifie to hear ſo vertuous a Prince thus caluminated.</p>
            <p>For my part I quiver and tremble in the carriage of my quill through this bloody and villeinous Scandall, and were it not for the Vulgar ſatisfaction, could think my ſelfe in no other predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then a Traytor, for preſuming to recterate over ſuch curſed and palpable yea moſt diabolicall Surmiſes, which is done by mee to indeavour the Subverſion or nipping in the bud of this In attoneable and moſt haynous peece of treaſon, and may that hand periſh that is endued with the leaſt ability, in writing that doth not ſtir in the defence of his righteous Soveraigne againſt theſe Hell littered Slanders, be it ever ſo little, ſet out thy good will in the defence of thy wrongfully defamed Prince, and that drone that doth not, deſerves not the benefit of breathing.</p>
            <p>Plead Oh <hi>England</hi> in the behalfe of thy beſt and juſteſt of Kings, examine thine owne conſcience, whether ever any King hath governed more righteouſly, or any people lived in more happineſſe and tranquillity, every Man enjoying the labor of his owne hands, and every one drinking of his owne Vineyard. No Ahab-like tiranny exerciſed by him, no leading into Captivity, or complayning in thy Streets, til their wicked Rebellion burſt forth, and ſince thy more impartiall conſcience may informe thee, how hee hath ever beene a labourer for peace, but when hee ſpake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them thereof, they made themſelves ready to battle, who ſate there to no other purpoſe, but to carouſe on the blood of Loyall Subjects, and to the extirpation of Monarchy root and branch, as that Pock rotten fire brand of Hell, the Parliaments <hi>Sardanapu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151809:4"/>not long ſince motioned to his Brethren of the ſame mould. Can thy underſtanding give way? were there an Ideom or forme ſhuffled for theſe unnaturall and in the higheſt nature ungodly invention to take the leaſt impreſſion on thy profeſſed Chriſtian beleefe? will not thy owne Genius tell thee, be thou never ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that hee who was next in ſucceſſion to the Crowne, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being as it were by reaſon of his Age on the brink of the Grave, (betweene whome there was ſuch mutuall and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall love) ſhould harbour a thought, much leſſe act, any thing that might either ſhorten his dayes by the courſe of nature ſo neerely come to a period, or if thou lay a ſide all thoughts of his Clemency (which were the greateſt point of inhumane unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe that might be lodged in the cancaredſt minde.) What would it availe a man to indeavour the diſtruction or death of an already dying man (the Lord of Heaven and Earth judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him and thoſe ſuggeſting Traytors, according to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe that is in him, according to the cleareneſſe of his hands in thy eye ſight.</p>
            <p>A few words more concerning that damnable lye, they ſay his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe was an Ague, and ſay they it was reſolved for his recovery, that nothing ſhould be given, or applyed to his Highneſſe by the way of Phyſick or Dyet, but by, and upon their generall advice and conſents. They ſay the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> (a Mortall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy to ſuch rebellious villaines as they are) after his inhibition, procured certain Plaiſters, and a certaine drink to be provided for his Majeſty, [ſurely of a contrary Nature, to that their Predeceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors preſented King <hi>John</hi> with) and they ſay that he againe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the like drinke and plaiſter for the King [ſtrong poyſon that muſt be ſo often uſed to carry away a dying Man] His Majeſtie dies, and within two yeares a Parliament is called [or which this is the very ſpawne] wherein many envious Machivilians [emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the dignities, and honours conferred on the Duke and him for them] ranſaked the innocent aſhes of the deceaſed King, and deepely taxing him of the former act amongſt themſelves, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe, thought to murther him for his Heroick merrrits, as they did the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> for feare of a Scourge for their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151809:4"/>ſo they too ſoon after procured the death of that Anti. Rebel by a deſperat and fatal hand, Our gracious K. that now is [they ſay] cleered him of that envious aſperſion, and they ſay themſelves that the former charge [or lye] was anſwered on the Dukes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and leaſt they ſhould murther that Engliſh Hero. The King diſſolved that Parliament. I would to God he had done the like now to prevent this, the Kingdomes meerely deſtructions, Now I pray you conſider whether it ſtands with reaſon, that the Duke being preferred to ſuch honours, that as beyond <hi>Hercules</hi> his Pillars. he could go no further, or be any greater unleſſe a King, which if thought of, was very contrarily contempted by cuting off the Aged King, having an heire of ſuch hopes I have before ſpoken of, the well known affection between our King and his Father, and who he was neerely come by the courſe of nature to his longeſt home. Alſo of the Chirurgions, and not only they but many more are now living of that profeſſion, then embalming the King, beſides inumerable proofes by Spectators.</p>
            <p>As for the rotten frame of that ſtinking lie concerning the plaiſter and drink, let al Loyall and Impartiall Phiſitians Judg, and againe, yea curſed forgers, God in a ſpecially manner threatens the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient with the like children, yea infallibly puniſheth them ſo, but the World never veilded more dutifull (and beyond expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) affectionate yſſue, then the royall branches of his ſacred Maj<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, but they have forgotten. Lex tallionis, Hammond, alias Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the jaylor; lately came to his Majeſty, and told him that if he had known what was in agutation, he would not have been ſo jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, his Majeſty demanded of him what, he anſwered they were drawing up a Bill to queſtion him for his life, a thing never heard of before, his Majeſty anſwered to this effect, that let them rake Hell, from whence their actions are derived, it ſhould not diſturbe him, being cleare in conſcience, Hammond then told the King, that if he had ſigned the laſt (trayterous) Bills, theſe laſt lies had not been publiſhed, If true? which the God of Heaven knowes to the contrary, then for their own ends they intended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale that incredible paricide, which, as I have ſhewed, he is as free from as the child unborne.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151809:5"/>
            <p>Compare their cunninger and more ſeeming pretences being [as thou ſeeſt] the worſt, but this off ſcumme of Helliſh plotts, with their proceedings ever ſince and left thine and the 3 King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes wofull experience dictate, whether any thing then profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, hath been ſince performed; what was it that they taught which either by corruption of inferiours, or their owne [if any] negligence had cauſed but was as ſoone granted as propoſed; was the proteſtant religion the cauſe? you ſee how that is moſt Athieſticallie renown'd and the moſt zealous profeſſors thereof perſecuted beyond hetheniſh cruelty.</p>
            <p>Was it the Kings Royal Prerogative? you know and all the world, that to be the worſt the Father of lyes and fountaine of Rebellion could invent, the King being Indungeoned, his vertuous Queene baſely traduced and baniſhed, a thing irkſome to the meaneſt Subject, the Royall object of our expectation expoſed, either to the cruell mercy of the Rebell, to be in his Fathers condition, or to leave his Crownes in Revertion, and ſo throw himſelfe to the wide world, which laſt reſolution hee took hold on, knowing the inevitable danger of comming into their crimſon curſed clawes, the reſt of the Royall iſſue unfortunatly falling into their clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, meerly daunce attendance on their Worſhips as Hoſpitall, or the meaner ſort of Almes people doe on their <hi>bene</hi> ſo do they on their Malefactors; then the liberty of the Subject you feele to your generall woe, is converted to the neverheard of before, cruill bondage, yea ſuch as was not knowne in any civill or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Warres.</p>
            <p>The laſt mentioned but firſt and fartheſt performed and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, were your priviledges of Parliament, but it is a legall one, when neither Towne or County, hath the free Election of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men? who are to negotiate every man for his Country, as faithfull ſervants of the Common wealth ought to do (and not inſtead of ſerving them) to Tyranize over them like Ægiptian Maſters as they have don ever ſince the ungodly beginning of their 7. yeares Raigne, Judge Oh Judge impartially what a conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath poore <hi>England</hi> been in ever ſince, and how theſe ſtates
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151809:5"/>
               <hi>Paracelſians</hi> who with their deſperate drugges or dregges have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the diſeaſe of a Nation (now moſt wofully languiſhing of it) would preſcribe a medicine worſe then the diſeaſe, by converting of that heavenly ordained government of Monarchie, into that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaicall and moſt unchriſtian like arbitray rule. Coraſives in ſtead of Cordials to a languiſhing Common wealth: Take an occaſion to peruſe all their paſſages and pauſe ſeriouſly upon them; and if thou findeſt not their former actions to bee in all reſpects diſagreeable to their profeſſions; then Ile give thee free diſpenſation (as I well may) to conceive and apprehend of theſe viperous aſperſions, according to thy owne judgement, no man (I thinke) oppoſing: Till when, or <hi>Calendas Graecas,</hi> I ſhall deſire all thoſe that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, to beware from ſuch ſcandalous doctrine of Devils, of which, never was heard the like: You (doubtleſſe) know how that the calling together, exerciſing and conducting of Land or Sea forces, ſolely belongs to the King, being the ſupreame head and governour of all ſuch his Kingdomes and Dominions. Tradition ſheweth this to everie of the meaneſt and ignorant men; and that he is the preſerver and protector of his Subjects, whether againſt oppreſſion or invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore know that he beareth not the ſword in vaine, as the ſaying hath it, <hi>Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſt parcere Subjectos &amp; debellare ſuperbos.</hi> Kings are for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncouragement of the good and the terrour of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe. But ſee the fomenters of this unnaturall and bloody Warre, unmasked and ſet out or preſented to the view of the World in their proper colours; ſome troubled ſpirits both of the Parliament and Citie firſt mentioned the extirpation of Epiſcopacie, roote and branch. Others of the like cut, in the ſame manner preferred a Bill for the transferring of the <hi>Militia</hi> of Sea and Land, out of his hands, whom God himſelfe had placed them in (our Soveraigne Lord the King) into the hands of ſuch Sectaries or other temporiſing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>otters, who (queſtionleſſe) were to part ſtakes with them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their. Rebellion might the eaſier take effect. And although the full convention of Parliament unanimouſly rejected theſe trayterous Bils, the main <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Agents in the buſineſſe revive and promote them by tumults and inſurrections. I ſhall deſire you to judge of the cauſe by the intended effect; and as a perjured villaine is never to have his Oath again, ſo I pray thee take not their tongues or pens for ſlanders,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151809:6"/>who have beene ſo often perjured: yea, would ſolemnly ſweare to the world (were it not for ſhame more then conſcience) that the ſun never ſhined. Never did that famous Oratour <hi>Cicero</hi> pronounce an Oration with more confidence and audacitie then their ſqueakers and other ſuch as <hi>Martin</hi> will babble Treaſon impudence, I ſhould ſay of them: But to the former diſcourſe, After this diſſertion, then began upon the Houſe of Peeres by the name of Biſhops, and Popiſh Lords, who (as they ſayde) hindred a free paſſage to their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And gathering to an head of the rabble rout of the Countrey, with a factious partie of the Citie, forced the Parliament as farre as they could; crying downe of Biſhops, and intollerably abuſing them as they paſt, with the ſame barbarous demeanour towards the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſe, that would not aſſent to their treaſon; neither would theſe now reciding at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> joyne to ſuppreſſe theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, being underhand not onely permitters but promoters of thoſe horrid deſignes. Not long after, were by their meanes, opprobrious words, yea moſt dangerous, ſpoken againſt his Majeſtie by the meaneſt that paſſed, ſaying (as it is well gathered by a Gentleman) that they would have no more Porters lodges; but would ſpeake with the King when they pleaſed: Judge whether the ſame ſpirit hath not had a powerfull influence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this laſt more horrid device. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie finding the danger that might enſue, accuſeth the chiefe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters to the Parliament, of high treaſon, being the Lord <hi>Kymbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and the five Members, the Articles are inſtanced in a Booke called <hi>Comparatis Comparandis;</hi> which Articles they have ever ſince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to prove, and indeed effectually performed, till it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to ſtay their furie. The Houſes being by this time corrupted, would not obey the King in ſequeſtring their Members; but rather encouraged them in their treaſon. Having ſent them to the Citie where they were not onely harboured, but in ſhort time the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Councell at <hi>London</hi> being illegally altered and unlawfull and unaccuſtomed watches kept in the Citie, under the command of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor — <hi>Skippon,</hi> pretended for the ſafetie of the Citie; the Trayned Bands guard thoſe Members from the Citie to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with many lights and long boats were ſent out loaden with Saker, murdering peeces, and other ammunition, dreſt up with waſte cloaths and ſtreamers, as ready to fight; the Marriners by water, the Soldiers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151809:6"/>by land, as they paſt by White hall asked what was become of the King, where was hee? And for all his Majeſties accuſation of the Members of high Treaſon, the prementioned revive their former treaſon for transferring the power by Sea and Land into other hands; withall the Commons deſiring the Lords concurrence in petitioning to the King that the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome might be transferred into ſuch hands as they would confide in, which was twice carryed negatively, by the voyces of much the major part of Lords; hereupon they (by the incenſed) meaner ſort, petition the Houſe of Commons, againſt the Lords as Malignants, and deſire to know their names, and threaten to remove them: and <hi>Hollis</hi> made a ſpeech to the Lords, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing that Petition at a Conference, whereupon diverſe Lords went away, and then that trayterous vote paſſed, being rejected twice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when neither popiſh Lords or Biſhops were preſent, twelve of the Biſhops being in the Tower: Since which time the lower Houſe carry what they will <hi>(Stat pro ratione voluntas)</hi> being gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the former impeached Members, having the rude multitude at their commands, wholy commanded the Houſe of Peeres to what they liſt, who dared not but ſubmit to any thing brought to them, for their concurrence: Judge whether it was ſafe reciding for a King, where his greateſt enemies were ſo prevalent, and he in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life daily, had even any King more reaſon to deſert enemies more dangerous? Now I leave it to any intelligible, and impartiall Chriſtian to diſcerne and judge of theſe viperous ſcandals; being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to publiſh this as an Antidote, while ſtronger lynes are in the Mint, the time permitting not a larger anſwer, yet the World may ſee them here beaten with their owne weapons: As they Allegeance bindeth thee, pray and ceaſe not for thy righteous Soveraigne, ſo mayſt thou and all true Subjects proſper.</p>
            <p>The next lye of any conſequence is that of <hi>Rochell,</hi> which by the loyall intelligence of a never failing Champion of the truth, I have obtained; (being gathered from no Weſtminſter like for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) but ſuch as ſhall make it appeare to be the very truth of the proceeding then agitated, which are thus. His Majeſties pious care in the ſufficient number of men, and ſhipping, his choice of the moſt experienced Souldiers of the three Kingdomes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151809:7"/>
               <hi>Burrowes, Rich, Hawley, Sant-Leager, Fryar, &amp;c.</hi> of Ireland, <hi>Willbughby, Croſly,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Bingley, &amp;c.</hi> of Scotland, Sir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Gray, Conningham, &amp;c.</hi> The hot and bloody fight at their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding argues no want of Commiſſion: At their landing there was much galantry ſhewed as might be in any action, where (at length) the French were forced to retreat, the Engliſh loſing many a gallant man, as Sir <hi>William Heydon, Johnſon</hi> the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer, Sir <hi>George Blundell,</hi> and others, and comming before the Fort, although there were many great Commanders, who I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume experienced in all feates of Warre, and would have beene much offended to be otherwiſe eſteemed; yet when they came to entrench and raiſe batteries, whether out or wilfullneſſe, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, who can judge? None could be found to undertake it, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>John Tradskine</hi> was made uſe of as chiefe workeman, and this is conceived to be one great cauſe of the miſcariage, &amp; long lying before the Fort, prevailing no further; and had not the ſea-men bravely performed their part, they would not have ſtayed ſo long. for the enemies were both skilfull and dilligent in keeping them from releiving, but ſurely God alone as is conceived they being no other but Sectaries though then profeſſed Proteſtants, wee were fruſtrated of our deſignes, which was this; intelligence being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that reliefe was comming, they drew their ſquadrons of ſhips, ſo that part as the wind then ſate, to be ready to receive them, the French accordingly ſet forth, and came on, but fell to the Lee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the Fort then was upon Articles of ſurrender, when ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly the winde chopt about, and ſo advantagious it was for the French, and contrary to the Engliſh, that is was not in the art of man to hinder, that advantage or rather providence: the French making uſe of their victory, neglected not in the purſuit, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage in the retreat, was either by the miſtake, or too much care to ſecure themſelves or ſome Officers, if not contrary, yet farre from the command of the Generall, and the Councell of Warre, and yet men eſteemed full of honour and long experience: and looke then on the King, then but yong, acting by his Councell, chooſing ſuch Officers of ſeverall Kingdomes, generally eſteemed of for honour, valour, and knowledge, ſparing no expences; Oh then judge equally taking your charity of a Loyall Subject along, whether thy pious Soveraigne, is not intollerably, yea moſt unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151809:7"/>ſlandred; Let every true Chriſtian ſhed a teare for theſe moſt opprobious callumnies, and God will (if he weepes with him that weepes) comfort him alſo in the day of his diſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>As concerning <hi>Rochell,</hi> after the Duke was ſlaine by <hi>Felton,</hi> when ready to put to ſea, did he not with all expedition make choice of the Earle of <hi>Lyndſey,</hi> a man full of honour, gallantry, and beloved of the Souldiery both by Sea and Land, his gallantry in Denmarke being freſh in memory, furniſhed with all ſorts of Ammunition, ſhips, and all other neceſſaries; and what doe their miraculous expectations extend unto? But they would have <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Joſhua, Sampſon, David</hi> or <hi>Judas Maccabeus,</hi> and yet all could not muſſell the mouthes of theſe ſlanderous Lyars: as for their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on his letters, ſuppoſe there be any overtures to or with that French King, they doe not ſuite with theſe actions, what uſe can be made of what is not underſtood; how frequent is it with Princes and Potentates to treate of Peace, and prepare for warre, and to write and to ſpeake of peace only to make their Adverſaries ſecure; yea even in the heate of warre to make over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Treaties, and to act quite contrary, this is ſhewed by all Hiſtories; but admit as is objected, that his Majeſty did only make a ſhew of warre, without any intention, and that he did at laſt leave the Rochellers to themſelves, and the Duke <hi>De Roane</hi> alſo, although his Kinſman, and queſtionleſſe not without a juſt cauſe, when he was informed that whatſoever pretences of the Proteſtant Religion were obtruded upon him, the intereſt of the King of Spaine was advanced, and it was diſcovered that his gold payd <hi>de Roanes</hi> friends: How great a Lover of Proteſtants he hath over beene is as well knowne, as his juſt deſire of Soveraignty over whom God apoynted him, in all Chriſtendome (if this were as indeed it was) the true cauſe, who can blame his Majeſtie to withdraw himſelfe, that his firſt intentions were reall, his Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer Records will teſtifie, his large expences, great gratuities to, and his Penſions to <hi>Mouſeir Sabeeze,</hi> and others, to encourage them; certainely he could (at firſt with good words) have kept his money, the Dukes Officers, and others are able to give more ample ſatisfaction; but it ſeemes ſtrange to me if this ſuffice not the King being ſatisfied how that their Religion was not as preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151809:8"/>(any thing) agreeing with the Proteſtant, but were, and are moſt that goe under the notion of Proteſtants in France, of the Hugoniſts Sect, as far from a Proteſtant, as God and Mammon, light and darkeneſſe, vertue and vice, ſo pernitious a Sect is that of the Hugoniſts, which Sect, (as I ſaid before) the Rochellers were of; nevertheleſſe all the while the King was not ſatisfied of their Religion, his actions then in that behalfe as I have layd downe before, will apparently manifeſt his forwardneſſe to relieve Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Iriſh inſurrection, I wonder thoſe grand Ones at Weſtminſter dare pronounce the word Rebell, they being the moſt impudent and inhumane that ever I read or heard of. How dare they tax the King as a countenancer or any way, encourager of thoſe diſcontented people in Ireland? ſurely his ſo gracious and frequent both Procl. and Declarations in that behalfe, cannot but in the higheſt nature both cleare and juſtifie him againſt theſe ſurmiſes. Read all his Declarations concerning the Iriſh, and therein finde his tender care of healing the ſores of the diſtreſſed Proteſtants there: Yea, offered to goe in his owne Perſon on that deſigne againſt the I riſh; but within a little theſe Rebells tooke occaſion to riſe in armes, and hindered all the proceedings againſt the Iriſh; yea (as all the Kingdome may know) have converted moſt part of men and money raiſed for the Iriſh ſervice, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this unnaturall and moſt bloody Rebellion in England.</p>
            <p>Men may be guided by their fancies, and as the deafe Adder that ſtops her eares at the voice of the Charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely, refuſe truth offered unto them; I can but leave ſuch (as they are queſtionleſly left to a reprobate ſence) to their owne ſelfe-willed conſtructions.</p>
            <p>There cannot be more innocency both pretended, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly proved then I have heerein ſet downe, though in few words; hath not that glorious Lampe of Gods glory, the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> beene taxed for a troubler of Iſraell; <hi>Paul</hi> factious, <hi>Joſeph</hi> by his incontinent Miſtris, chaſte <hi>Hippolitus,</hi> religious and civill <hi>Suſanna, Eugenius, Athanaſius</hi> his name converted to <hi>Sathancthius;</hi> yea often taxed a murtherer of <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Scipio,</hi> and traduced before the Senate at Rome, as our gracious Soveraigne is before and by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151809:8"/>his trayterous Servants at Weſtminſter.</p>
            <p>Was not that ſplendifferous object of the Goſpels advancement Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> ſlandered by the Romiſh Prieſts for his pious confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Euſtochium, Paula, Demetriades, Paulina,</hi> with ſuch chaſte and devout women? Was not Chriſt himſelfe ſaid to be a Samaritan, and to have a Devill, with other odious as blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as reprooffes? Then in immitation of our bleſſed Saviour; Let our gracious Soveraign be barked at by all the inteſtine Zoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſes of the world, while they with aſpiring <hi>Phaeton,</hi> or too much confiding <hi>Icarus,</hi> truſt to fallicids, and God doubtleſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares a lanthorne for his Anoynted.</p>
            <p>I ſee the time drawes on, and that I can no longer paſſe the picturing of theſe antipodized times: Let the Loyall daigne the view of me, and the infected take though ſharpe to cure their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, and this is the <hi>ultimum</hi> of my honeſt and loyall endeavours: God Almighty bleſſe them that bleſſe him, and curſe them that curſe him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
